Guide to the John Sawyer Brooks Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John Sawyer Brooks papers
1846-2000
1851-1859
GEN MSS 1435
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.29
(11 boxes)
The John Sawyer Brooks Papers contain correspondence, scrapbooks, photographs and drawings, and other papers, most relating to missionaries and mission administration at the Mendi Mission in Sierra Leone, 1851-1859. Also present are papers relating to the Mount Pleasant Mission in Peel Township, Ontario, 1846-1855, and to the Brooks family, 1850s-circa 2000.
Brooks, John Sawyer, 1823-1864
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 5-8, 11: Restricted fragile material. May not be seen without the permission of the appropriate curator.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1846-1859. II. Scrapbooks, 1846-1859. III. Photographs and Drawings, 1840s-1927. IV. Other Papers, 1849-2000.
John Sawyer Brooks (1823-1864)
John Sawyer Brooks (1823-1864), American clergyman and missionary. Brooks was born in Groton, Massachusetts, a son of Rufus Brooks (1800-1892) and Mary Wood Sawyer Brooks (1803-1876). His siblings included Asa Whitcomb Brooks (1821-1862) and Jonathan Brooks (circa 1837-1862), both of whom died in the Battle of Fair Oaks, Virginia, while serving in the 16th Massachusetts Infantry Regiment during the Civil War; Sarah Brooks Pierce (1832-1929), whose home in Greenfield, Massachusetts, was an underground railroad safe house; and Rebecca Stone Brooks Simmons (1840-). John Sawyer Brooks married Fidelia Coburn (1805-1850) in 1847, and during 1842-1847 both worked as missionaries among fugitives from American slavery at Mount Pleasant Mission, founded by the American Abolition Society in Peel Township, Queen's Bush Settlement, Ontario. In 1850, they succeeded George Thompson at the American Missionary Association's Mendi Mission in, Sierra Leone. Fidelia Coburn Brooks died in York, Sierra Leone, in 1850; in 1855 Brooks married Susan Teall, also formerly a missionary in Queen's Bush Settlement, who died in 1855 in Good Hope Station, Sierra Leone. John Sawyer Brooks continued to work as a missionary at the Mendi Mission until 1861. He died in Sierra Leone in 1864.
The American Missionary Association and the Mendi Mission
The American Missionary Association was founded in New York City in 1846 by Congregational and other Christian missionaries advocating abolition of slavery. In 1846, the Association merged with the Union Missionary Society and assumed direction of the Mendi Mission, founded in 1842 by the Society and former Amistad captives at Kaw Mendi, Sierra Leone, in the present Bonthe District, near Sherbro Island. George Thompson (-1893) worked as a missionary at the Mendi Mission, arriving in 1848, and was followed by other missionaries, including John Sawyer Brooks and Fidelia Coburn Brooks in 1850. During 1850-1854, the Mission opened Tissana, Mo Tappan, and Boom Falls Stations in the interior and Good Hope Station on Sherbro Island. The Mendi Mission and its stations were transferred to the Church of the United Brethern in Christ in 1882.
Sources:
Beard, Augustus Field. A Crusade of Brotherhood: a History of the American Missionary Association (New York, AMS Press, 1972)
Thompson, George. Thompson in Africa (New York: printed for the author, 1854)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Candace Brown on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, the Chandler White and Philena Pennell Smith Acquisitions Fund, and the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2017.
Scope and Contents
The John Sawyer Brooks Papers contain correspondence, scrapbooks, photographs and drawings, and other papers, most relating to missionaries and mission administration at the Mendi Mission in Sierra Leone, 1851-1859. Also present are papers relating to missionaries in Queen's Bush Settlement, Ontario, 1846-1855, and to the Brooks family, 1850s-circa 2000.
Most correspondence, 1851-1859 and undated, consists of letters, some with reports and financial accounts, to Brooks from American Missionary Association officials, Mendi Mission missionaries and other employees, and members of the Mission church and students at the Mission school. Also present are letters from Brooks, some with drawings of Mendi Mission scenes, and letterpress copies of letters from Brooks, 1855-1859, to many of the same correspondents and to members of the Brooks family. Four scrapbooks contain additional similar correspondence, 1846-1859, and clippings from unidentified newspapers, probably 1850s, about religion, abolition, and missionary work, including articles about the Mendi Mission, George Thompson, John Sawyer Brooks, and Susan Teall Brooks. Correspondents in letters and scrapbooks include American Missionary Association officials Lewis Tappan and George Whipple; missionaries T. G. Cole, D. K. Flickinger, A. W. Hanson, David J. Lee, Hannah More, Morris Officer, J. Cutler Tefft, and George Thompson; phonographer Isaac Pitman, including letters in phonetic English, with printed material about phonetic English; and Brooks's sisters, Sarah Brooks Pierce and Rebecca Stone Brooks Simmons.
Other papers relating to the Mendi Mission include autograph manuscript sermons and sermon notes by Brooks, 1859 and undated; autograph manuscript compositions by students at the Mission school, 1854 and undated; printed treaties relating to war in Sierra Leone, 1849-1853; a manuscript document transferring ownership of a slave to the Mission, undated; other legal and administrative documents, 1853-1855 and undated; Mendi Garamo, a printed publication about the Mende language, 1857 October; an issue of The Early Dawn, a newspaper published in Good Hope, Sherbro Island, 1861 May; and drawings by Brooks of Mendi Mission and other African scenes, 1850s.
Papers relating to missionaries in Queen's Bush Settlement, Ontario, include a small amount of correspondence of Fidelia Coburn Brooks, 1846; letters to Brooks from Susan Teall Brooks, 1853-1855; legal documents relating to Brooks, 1849; and drawings by Brooks of mission buildings, 1840s. In addition to correspondence, papers relating to the Brooks family include an ambrotype of John Sawyer Brooks, 1850s-1860s, and photographs of his parents, Rufus Brooks and Mary Wood Sawyer Brooks, 1870s-1890; his brothers Asa Whitcomb Brooks and Jonathan Brooks, circa 1862; and his sisters, Rebecca Stone Brooks Simmons and Sarah Brooks Pierce, and her daughter, Susanne Fidelia Pierce, circa 1880 and 1927.
Antislavery movements -- United States; Abolitionists -- Massachusetts; Abolitionists -- Ontario -- Queen's Bush Settlement; Clergy -- Sierra Leone; English language -- Phonetics; Fugitive slaves -- Ontario -- Queen's Bush Settlement; Mende language -- Sierra Leone; Missionaries -- Ontario -- Queen's Bush Settlement; Missionaries -- Sierra Leone; Missionary settlements -- Ontario -- Queen's Bush Settlement; Missionary settlements -- Sierra Leone; Missions -- Ontario -- Queen's Bush Settlement; Missions -- Sierra Leone; Slavery -- Sierra Leone; Slavery -- United States; Peel (Ont.: Regional municipality) -- Religion -- 19th century; Queen's Bush Settlement (Ont.) -- Religion -- 19th century; Sierra Leone -- Description and travel; Sierra Leone -- Politics and government -- 1808-1896; Sierra Leone -- Religion -- 19th century; Sierra Leone -- Social conditions -- To 1961; Ambrotypes (photographs); Cabinet photographs; Visiting cards; Drawings (visual works); Letterpress copybooks -- Sierra Leone -- 19th century; Photographs; Scrapbooks -- Sierre Leone -- 19th century; Sermons -- Sierre Leone -- 19th century; Clergy -- Ontario -- Queen's Bush Settlement -- 19th century; Clergy -- Sierra Leone -- 19th century; Missionaries -- Ontario -- Queen's Bush Settlement -- 19th century; Missionaries -- Sierra Leone -- 19th century; Early dawn; Brooks, Asa Whitcomb, 1821-1862; Brooks, Fidelia Coburn, 1805-1850; Brooks, John Sawyer, 1823-1864; Brooks, Jonathan, approximately 1837-1862; Brooks, Mary Wood Sawyer, 1803-1876; Brooks, Rufus, 1800-1892; Brooks, Susan Teall, -1855; Brooks family; Cole, T. G.; Flickinger, D. K. (Daniel Kumler), 1824-1911; Hanson, A. W.; Lee, David J.; More, Hannah, 1808-1868; Officer, Morris, 1823-1874; Pierce, Sarah Brooks, 1832-1929; Pitman, Isaac, 1813-1897; Simmons, Rebecca Stone Brooks, 1840-; Tappan, Lewis, 1788-1873; Tefft, J. Cutler, -1855; Thompson, George, -1893; Whipple, George, 1805-1876; American Abolition Society; American Missionary Association; Amistad (Schooner); United States. Army. Massachusetts Infantry Regiment, 16th -- Pictorial works
- Correspondence, 1846-1859, undated; Series I; 1.25; 4 boxes
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Letters, 1846 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 55)
  - Letters, 1851-1852 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1853 January-June (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1853 July (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1853 August (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 56)
  - Letters, 1853 August-December (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1853 (Box 11, Folder 61)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted fragile material. May not be seen without the permission of the appropriate curator.
  - Letters, 1854 January-February (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1854 March (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1854 April-May (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1854 June-July (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters, 1854 August-September (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters, 1854 October-November (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters, 1854 November (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 57)
  - Letters, 1854 December (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters, 1854 (Box 11, Folder 62)
  - Letters, 1855 January-February (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters, 1855 March-April (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters, 1855 May (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters, 1855 June-July (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Letters, 1855 August-September (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Letters, 1855 October-November (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Letters, 1855 December (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Letters, 1855 (Box 11, Folder 63)
  - Letters, 1856 January-March (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Letters, 1856 April (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Letters, 1856 May (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Letters, 1856 June (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Letters, 1856 July (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Letters, 1856 August (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Letters, 1856 September (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Letters, 1856 October-November (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Letters, 1856 December (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Letters, 1856 December (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 58)
  - Letters, 1857 January-February (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Letters, 1857 January-February (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 59)
  - Letters, 1857 March-May (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Letters, 1857 June-July (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Letters, 1858-1859 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Letters, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Letters, undated (Box 11, Folder 64)
  - Letters (fragments), undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Letterpress copybook, 1855-1857 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Letterpress copybook, 1857-1859 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Scrapbooks, 1846-1859; Series II; 0.33; 4 boxes
  Arranged chronologically
  - Scrapbook, 1846-1855 (Box Box 5 (Oversize))
  - Scrapbook, 1852-1857 (Box Box 6 (Oversize))
  - Scrapbook, 1856-1858 (Box Box 7 (Oversize))
  - Scrapbook, 1857-1859 (Box Box 8 (Oversize))
- Photographs and Drawings, 1840s-1927, undated; Series III; 0.21; part of 1 box
  - Brooks, John Sawyer (ambrotype), [1850s-1860s] (Box 11, Folder 66)
  - Brooks, Rufus (cabinet photographs), 1890 (Box 9, Folder 36)
  - Brooks, Mary Wood Sawyer (carte-de-visite and drawing), [circa 1870] (Box 9, Folder 37)
  - Brooks, Asa Whitcomb; Brooks, Jonathan; and United States Army, Massachusetts Infantry Regiment, 16th (reproductions of photographs), [circa 1862] (Box 9, Folder 38)
  - Pierce, Sarah Brooks; Simmons, Rebecca Stone Brooks; and Pierce, Susan Fidelia (cabinet photograph, drawing, and photograph), [circa 1880], 1927 (Box 9, Folder 39)
  - Unidentified people (photographs), [circa 1900] (Box 9, Folder 40)
  - Mount Pleasant Mission (drawings), [1840s] (Box 9, Folder 41)
  - Mendi Mission and unidentified places (drawings), [1850s] (Box 9, Folder 42)
- Other Papers, 1849-2000, undated; Series IV; 0.21; part of 1 box
  - Advertisement for phonetic English publications. Print (London: Fred. Pitman; Bath: Isaac Pitman), undated (Box 9, Folder 43)
  - Clipping about Sarah Brooks Pierce (photocopy), [circa 2000] (Box 9, Folder 44)
  - The Early Dawn, Vol. 1, No. 3. Print (unidentified publisher: Good Hope, Sherbro Island), 1861 May (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 60)
  - Legal and administrative documents relating to the Mendi Mission, 1853-1855, undated (Box 9, Folder 45)
  - Legal and administrative documents relating to the Mendi Mission, 1854 (Box 11, Folder 65)
  - Legal documents relating to the Mount Pleasant Mission, 1849 (Box 9, Folder 46)
  - Mendi Garamo, Nr. 2. Print (unidentified place and publisher), 1857 October (Box 9, Folder 47)
  - Notes about farming in Africa, undated (Box 9, Folder 48)
  - Peace treaty between Sierra Leone, Great Britain, Careybah Caulker, and Thomas Stephen Caulker. Print (no place or publisher), 1849-1853 (Box 9, Folder 49)
  - Poems, undated (Box 9, Folder 50)
  - Sermons and sermon notes, 1859, undated (Box 9, Folder 51-52)
  - Talisman text, in Arabic, undated (Box 9, Folder 53)
  - Writings of Mendi Mission students, 1854, undated (Box 9, Folder 54)